Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today’s דף daf is קי״ג Kuf Yud
Gimmel officially where we’re a little behind we start with the קי״ב
עמוד ב׳ Kuf Yud Bet Amud Bet with the משנה Mishnah and
a new פרק perek חרש Cheresh and basically the whole משנה Mishnah
takes up this עמוד ב׳ Amud Bet and we’ve pretty much read
this משנה Mishnah when it’s come up in pieces in the previous
פרקים perakim so we’re going to go through it pretty quickly. So
let’s take a look.
חרש שנשא פקחת Cheresh shenasa pika’chat a deaf person marries a hearing
woman ופיקח שנשא
חרשת upike’ach shenasa chereshet a hearing person marries a deaf woman אם
רצה להוציא יוציא ואם רצה לקיים יקיים im ratza lehotzi yotzi ve’im
ratza lekayem yekayem if he wants to divorce he can divorce and
if he wants to keep the marriage he can keep it because
again דאורייתא De’oraita there’s no קידושין kidushin he’s not
if one of the people is deaf as we know halachically they’re
not considered to be a בר דעת bar da’at which is actually
an issue we’re going to get to today about how much is
a חרש cheresh sort of disqualified or considered out of the sort
of category of legal agency
and that’s of course the assumption here that changes over time as
well post-גמרא Gemara as schools for the deaf develop etc. but obviously
in the משנה Mishnah that’s assumed so therefore the קידושין kidushin is
only rabbinic if one of the people is deaf or deaf-mute more
specifically but the same way the marriage was rabbinic the divorce can
also be rabbinic and the rabbis will allow the divorce the same
way they created the marriage. So if he wants to divorce he
can if he wants to keep the marriage he can. כשם שכונס
ברמיזה כך הוא מוציא ברמיזה Keshem shekones biremizah kach hu motzi biremizah
the same way he brings in with gesturing he can also divorce
her with gesturing which means that
now the same way he’s not speaking he’s not talking and so
on it’s all done through him expressing himself through gestures so the
same way anyway we allow a marriage in that situation we also
allow a divorce in that situation.
פיקח שנשא פקחת ונסתחרשה Pike’ach shenasa pika’chat venistacharesha now a hearing person
married a hearing woman and then she became a חרשת chereshet so
it’s a קידושין דאורייתא kidushin De’oraita now because they were married when
they were both hearing. אם רצה יוציא ואם רצה יקיים Im ratza
yotzi ve’im ratza yekayem he actually can divorce her because again because
divorce is unilateral coming from the man as long as the man
is hearing he can divorce her even though she is not hearing
and therefore not considered a בת דעת. bat da’at. The גמרא Gemara
will say the same way a man can divorce—well the משנה Mishnah
will say that let’s keep on reading. נשתטית לא יוציא Nishtatit lo
yotzi
however if she became not just deaf but if she became a
שוטה shotah a woman not in her right mind then he cannot
divorce her and the reason is it’s rabbinic in order to prevent
people from taking abuse of her because she will be a woman
who cannot protect herself against sexual abuse or sexual exploitation. לא יוציא.
Lo yotzi. נתחרש הוא או נשתטה Nitcharesh hu o nishtateh
if he however became a חרש cheresh or a שוטה shotah so
he’s not considered a בר דעת bar da’at then אינו מוציא עולמית
eino motzi olamit he can never divorce her because he is the
one who has to write the גט get and he is not
able
to legally able to he might practically be able to but he’s
not legally able to so therefore he can never divorce her. Okay
so moving on hold on one second okay so—is
that because it’s not rabbinic?
Correct because exactly because it works both ways exactly because they were
married when they were both hearing. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי Amar
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri said Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri מפני מה האישה
שנתחרשה יוצאה והאיש שנתחרש אינו מוציא? mipnei mah ha’ishah shenitcharesha yotza veha’ish
shenitcharesh eino motzi?
What’s the difference? Why when she becomes deaf after they were married
דאורייתא De’oraita when they were both hearing can she be divorced but
when he becomes deaf they cannot? אמרו לו Amru lo they said
to him אינו דומה האיש מגרש לאישה מתגרשת eino domeh ha’ish megeresh
la’ishah mitgareshet
it’s not the same a man who’s divorcing to a woman who’s
being divorced שהאישה יוצאה לרצונה ושלא לרצונה sheha'ishah yotza lirtzonah veshela lirtzonah
a woman is divorced with her will and against her will so
therefore she does not really she’s not really a member a participant
in the proceedings she’s really here an object as it were so
therefore she doesn’t have to be a בת דעת bat da’at it’s
the man who’s doing it והאיש אינו מוציא אלא לרצונו veha'ish eino
motzi ela lirtzono but the man does it only with his will
so he has to be considered an agent and a בר דעת.
bar da’at. העיד רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא He’id Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada
Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada testified על החרשת שהשיאה אביה al hachereshet shehishi’ah
aviha a deaf-mute woman that
her father married her when she was a minor so that would
be an example where she might have started as deaf but the
marriage was דאורייתא De’oraita because the father was the one who was
effecting the marriage it was done when she was a minor so
it was a biblical marriage שיוצאה בגט sheyotza beget that the husband
could divorce her with a גט. get.
So that’s very similar a biblical marriage but it’s the woman who
is the person who is deaf and the man could still divorce
her. אמרו לו Amru lo so they said to Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri look this is what יוחנן בן גודגדא Yochanan ben Gudgada said
so אף זו כיוצא בה af zu kayotza bah
our case would just be like it when she started off hearing
and became deaf same story the man could still do it. Very
interesting תוספות Tosafot העיד רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא He’id Rabbi Yochanan ben
Gudgada תוספות Tosafot says רבנן הביאו לבית המדרש להביא ראיה לדבריהם. rabbanan
hevi’u le’veit hamidrash lehavi re’ayah ledivreihem. מאמרו לו אף זו כיוצא בה
meamru lo af zu kayotze bah תוספות Tosafot says like here
we're going to prove it. יוחנן בן גדגדא, Yochanan ben Gudgada, come
here, we got come tell us,
which I like the הביאו לבית המדרש, heviu leveit hamidrash, like he
was a person who normally wasn't in the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash,
but they asked him to come to prove their point. Okay, back
to the גמרא. Gemara.
So that's the issue about one of them being if the marriage
was rabbinic, they could be divorced, she could be divorced, if it
was דאורייתא de'oraita only if he is still a בר דעת. bar
da'at. And now we get to the section that we've read before,
but
I'm going to go through it very quickly. שני אחים חרשים נשואים
לשתי אחיות חרשות, shnei achim chereshim nesu'im lishtei achayot cherashot, two deaf
brothers married to two deaf sisters. And then we're going to go
through or the sisters are not deaf, but it doesn't matter since
the brothers are, it's only rabbinic קידושין. kiddushin. או לשתי אחיות פקחות,
o lishtei achayot pikchot, or they both the sisters are hearing. או
לאחת חרשת ולאחת פקחת, o leachhat chereshet uleachhat pikechhat, or one is
hearing, one is deaf. Or the reverse, both sisters are deaf and
then it doesn't really matter what the brothers are. או שתי אחיות
חרשות נשואות לשני אחים פקחים, o shtei achayot cherashot nesu'ot lishnei achim
pikchim, so they're both deaf and the brothers are hearing. או לשני
אחים חרשים, o lishnei achim chereshim, or both brothers are deaf. או
לשני אחים אחד חרש ואחד פקח, o lishnei achim echad cheresh ve'echad
pikeach, one is hearing, one is deaf. בקיצור, bekitzur, two brothers married
to two sisters, but it's all rabbinic because two of the either
the brothers or the sisters are deaf. So in that case, הרי
אלו פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום. harei elu peturot min hachalitzah umin
hayibum. If one of them dies, you're exempt from חליצה chalitzah and
יבום, yibum, because it's the case of wife's sister and it's all
operating in the same plane because it's all we're dealing with two
rabbinic marriages of people that are deaf. So, פטורות מן החליצה ומן
היבום. peturot min hachalitzah umin hayibum. ואם היו נכריות יכנסו, ve'im hayu
nochriyot yichnesu, if the sisters were not if the women were not
sisters, were unrelated, then you could do יבום. yibum. ואם רצו להוציא,
ve'im ratzu lehotzi, and if you want to give a גט get
after יבום, yibum, יוציאו, yotzi'u, you can give a גט. get. But
what you cannot do, at least in some of them, is חליצה,
chalitzah, because you can't do חליצה chalitzah if one of the members
there is a חרש. cheresh. Right, if the woman's a חרשת, chereshet,
she can't do חליצה. chalitzah. If the man's a חרש, cheresh, he
can't do it. Because they so therefore since one of the people
we're dealing with minimally is a חרש, cheresh, חליצה chalitzah is not
an option. שני אחים אחד חרש ואחד פקח. shnei achim echad cheresh
ve'echad pikeach. Now
you have two brothers, however one is hearing and one is deaf.
נשואים לשתי אחיות פקחות, nesu'im lishtei achayot pikchot, and they're married to
two sisters, both of whom are hearing. So you've got one דאורייתא
de'oraita marriage and one דרבנן derabbanan with the guy who's the deaf
person is the דרבנן derabbanan marriage. מת חרש בעל הפקחת. met cheresh
ba'al hapikechhat. So the deaf
person the deaf man dies. מה יעשה פקח בעל הפקחת? mah ya'aseh
pikeach ba'al hapikechhat? What does the hearing brother do who's married to
the hearing woman? So basically, he now is dealing with his wife's
sister, and he's married to the woman he's married to is a
biblical קידושין, kiddushin, right? Because they're hearing. And now he's got his
wife's sister. So תצא משום אחות אשה, tetzei mishum achot isha, so
the woman walks away, that's easy enough. It's a biblical case of
wife's sister, walks away. מת פקח בעל הפקחת. met pikeach ba'al hapikechhat.
Now let's say the hearing brother dies. So the deaf brother, this
woman also is his wife's sister now. But the problem is his
wife is not his biblical wife, because it was only a rabbinic
marriage. So what is he going to do? He can't she can't
walk away because the guy isn't really married to his wife דאורייתא.
de'oraita. On the other end, he can't do יבום yibum because it's
rabbinically it's because whatever, it's his wife's sister. So
מה יעשה חרש בעל הפקחת? mah ya'aseh cheresh ba'al hapikechhat? מוציא את
אשתו בגט ואשת אחיו אסורה לו לעולם. motzi et ishto beget ve'eshet
achiv asurah lo le'olam. He's really struck stuck.
He has to divorce his wife. He can't keep on living with
his wife because to keep on living with his wife, it would
be אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. He cannot now
why does
he
why is his brother's wife forbidden forever? Why can't he do חליצה?
chalitzah? Because he's a
חרש. cheresh. Okay, he's a חרש, cheresh, so he can't do חליצה.
chalitzah. Why can't he do יבום? yibum? Because then he would be
having sex with his wife or ex-wife's sister. So she is stuck.
שני אחים פקחים נשואים לשתי אחיות. shnei achim pikchim nesu'im lishtei achayot.
Now two hearing brothers married to two sisters. אחת חרשת ואחת פקחת.
achat chereshet ve'achat pikechhat. So now rather than the brothers being one
of each, it's the sisters that's one of each. מת פקח בעל
החרשת. met pikeach ba'al hachereshet.
The guy married to the to the deaf sister dies. Okay. So
now the guy married to the hearing sister, he's got a case
of wife's sister, but it's a biblical wife's sister. He's married to
his wife biblically. So מה יעשה פקח בעל הפקחת? mah ya'aseh pikeach
ba'al hapikechhat? תצא משום אחות אשה. tetzei mishum achot isha. So that's
easy, so the woman walks away, because the guy that's the surviving
brother is biblically married to his wife. So this is wife's sister,
she walks away משום אחות אשה. mishum achot isha. מת פקח בעל
הפקחת. met pikeach ba'al hapikechhat. But it's more complicated when the hearing
brother dies. מה יעשה פקח בעל החרשת? mah ya'aseh pikeach ba'al hachereshet?
What does the hearing brother do who's survived, but he's married to
the woman who is deaf, which is only a rabbinic marriage. So
now he's faced again with wife's sister, but he can't walk away
because his marriage is to a woman who is only rabbinic. So
מוציא את אשתו בגט, motzi et ishto beget, so he divorces his
wife. Can't keep on living with his wife, that would be אחות
זקוקתו. achot zekukato. But now, this אשת אחיו בחליצה. eshes achiv b'chalitzah.
You have the option of חליצה. chalitzah. Since he is hearing, it
was his wife who was deaf, right? He's hearing, so he can
now do חליצה chalitzah with his wife's sister. Is everybody with me?
I'm doing this a little quickly, but people are basically getting the
gist here? Okay, so we did this before. Okay. I only got
one yes to that question.
Okay.
שני אחים אחד חרש ואחד פקח נשואים לשתי אחיות אחת חרשת ואחת
פקחת. shnay achim echad cheresh v'echad pikeach nesuim l'shtei achayos achas chereshes
v'achas pikeachas. If you have one of each on both sides, and
again, two brothers married to two sisters, and the deaf man is
married to the deaf woman, מת חרש בחרשת מה יעשה פקח בפקחת?
mes cheresh b'chereshes mah yaaseh pikeach b'pikeachas? So if the deaf man
married to the deaf woman died, what does the hearing man do?
So again, same story. This is his wife's sister. He's biblically married
to his wife. This is the hearing man and the hearing woman,
so she walks away. תצא משום אחות אשה. tetzei mishum achos isha.
That's always easy, right? That case. מת פקח בפקחת מה יעשה חרש
בחרשת? mes pikeach b'pikeachas mah yaaseh cheresh b'chereshes? Now the hearing man
married to the hearing woman dies. And now you've got the deaf
man married to the deaf woman, case of wife's sister, but again
it's only rabbinic because it was only a rabbinic קידושין. kiddushin. So
מה יעשה חרש בחרשת? mah yaaseh cheresh b'chereshes? מוציא אשתו בגט. motzi
ishto b'get. He has
to divorce his wife because that's אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso because now
he has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum with his wife's sister.
ואשת אחיו אסורה לעולם. v'eshes achiv asura l'olam. Back to that story
though. His brother's wife, he, this guy is a חרש. cheresh. So
he's a חרש, cheresh, he can't do חליצה, chalitzah, he can't do
יבום yibbum because that would be sex with his ex-wife's sister. So
she is always forbidden. שני אחים. shnay achim. So that was all
the permutations of two sisters, two brothers and two sisters. Now we're
going to do two brothers and two unrelated women. שני אחים אחד
חרש ואחד פקח נשואים לשתי נכריות פקחות. shnay achim echad cheresh v'echad
pikeach nesuim l'shtei nachriyos pikeachos. Two brothers married to two unrelated women,
okay, but the brothers are one of each. מת חרש בפקחת מה
יעשה פקח בפקחת? mes cheresh b'pikeachas mah yaaseh pikeach b'pikeachas?
So the deaf brother died. So what does this guy do? So
now he's got a rabbinic מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum with his
brother's, you know, his deaf brother's wife. So that was a rabbinic
קידושין, kiddushin, rabbinic מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum. The women are unrelated.
So fine. או חולץ או מייבם. o choletz o meyabem. Do whatever
you want, either חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibbum. מת פקח בפקחת מה
יעשה חרש בפקחת? mes pikeach b'pikeachas mah yaaseh cheresh b'pikeachas? So now
the hearing brother dies. So the brother who is deaf, what does
he do? So again, he has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום דאורייתא,
yibbum d'oraisa, by the way, I we should point out he has
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, right? Because his brother was married,
his hearing brother was married to this woman biblically. So he's a
דאורייתא מצוה d'oraisa mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, but this woman is unrelated
to his wife. So again, do what you want. So מה יעשה
חרש בפקחת כונס ואינו מוציא לעולם. mah yaaseh cheresh b'pikeachas kones v'eino
motzi l'olam. But no, it's a little restricted. He can't do what
he wants. He's a חרש. cheresh. So one thing he's not able
to do is חליצה. chalitzah. So his only option when faced with
his brother's wife is יבום. yibbum. Now after he does יבום, yibbum,
he can't say, okay, fine, you did יבום, yibbum, now divorce her
so she can go marry somebody else. No. He's a חרש. cheresh.
He can't give a גט. get. Okay? So here you have, meaning
this is a very simple case with all the complications. Basically it
says what does a חרש cheresh do who's faced with a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום? yibbum? He can't do חליצה chalitzah because he's a
חרש. cheresh. He can only do יבום, yibbum, and after יבום yibbum
he can't do a גט get because he's a חרש. cheresh. So
bottom line, what it's saying is a חרש cheresh who has to
do יבום yibbum can only do יבום yibbum and they can never
get divorced.
Right, but at least then he's sort of choosing whether to get
married... well that's not true. When a חרש... cheresh... no, thank you
for bringing that back. That's the first point of the משנה. mishnah.
That's what this is in contrast to. When a חרש cheresh gets
married, it's only a rabbinic קידושין, kiddushin, so he can also get
divorced rabbinically. But when a חרש cheresh does יבום, yibbum, it's a
biblical act of יבום, yibbum, right? So because יבום yibbum is done
more by the physical reality of having sex and it carries over
the קידושין kiddushin from the brother, even though the person is a
חרש cheresh and not considered בר דעת, bar daas, the יבום yibbum
is still binding דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So thank you. Yes, that's exactly what
this... when you get through all of these various permutations, the clear
point here is contrasting to the first case. When a חרש cheresh
gets married, he can also get divorced. When a חרש cheresh does
יבום, yibbum, it's דאורייתא d'oraisa and he can't get divorced. So therefore,
and the woman is stuck anyway, because the woman, she can't walk
away from this situation, she doesn't have חליצה, chalitzah, right? So besides
the חרש, cheresh, you know, whatever, they're both sort of stuck. The
only option here is יבום yibbum and then no divorce. Okay, although
if he would shirk... he could always shirk his responsibilities, which wouldn't
be, you know... she is really stuck. Okay,
so where were we? מה יעשה חרש בפקחת כונס ואינו מוציא לעולם
שני אחים פקחים. mah yaaseh cheresh b'pikeachas kones v'eino motzi l'olam shnay
achim pikchim.
Now two hearing brothers
married to two unrelated women. נשואים לשתי נכריות אחת פקחת ואחת חרשת.
nesuim l'shtei nachriyos achas pikeachas v'achas chereshes. אחת פקחת ואחת חרשת, achas
pikeachas v'achas chereshes, one is hearing and one is deaf. מת פקח
בחרשת מה יעשה פקח בפקחת? mes pikeach b'chereshes mah yaaseh pikeach b'pikeachas?
So the man married to the deaf woman died. So what does
the man married to the hearing woman do? So again, it's a
biblical... he can do whatever... he, I mean, he's hearing, so the
woman is not related to his wife, he can do whatever he
wants, except because the woman is deaf, she can't be part of
a חליצה chalitzah ceremony. So the only option, you got it? So
what do you have... meaning bottom line, what does a man do
if he has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum with a deaf
woman, with his brother was married to a deaf woman? So he
can't do חליצה chalitzah because she can't do חליצה chalitzah because she's
deaf.
matter that the
woman wasn't. That's the principle we laid at the beginning of the
משנה. mishnah.
So what can he do? כונס, kones, he can marry, he does
ביאה, biah, he can do יבום. yibum. ואם רצה להוציא יוציא, v'im
ratza l'hotzi yotzi, he can give a גט get even though she's
deaf. That's the principle we pointed out in the beginning. That as
long as the man is hearing, he can give a גט get
even by a דאורייתא d'oraisa קידושין. kiddushin. מת פיקח בן פיקחת מה
יעשה פיקח בן חרשת. meis pikeach ben pikachas mah ya'aseh pikeach ben
chereshes. Now what about if the brother died? So now you have
a hearing sister and a hearing brother who has a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום. yibum. He's married to a woman who's deaf, but what
difference does it make? This woman isn't related. So then he has
all the options. So מה יבא או חולץ או מייבם, mah yavo
o choletz o meyabem, either חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum. שני אחים
אחד חרש ואחד פיקח נשואים לשתי נכריות אחת חרשת ואחת פיקחת. shnei
achim echad cheresh v'echad pikeach nesu'im l'shtei nochriyos achas chereshes v'achas pikachas.
You have one of each and they're married to the same type.
מת חרש בן חרשת מה יעשה פיקח בן פיקחת. meis cheresh ben
chereshes mah ya'aseh pikeach ben pikachas. So the deaf man who was
married to the deaf woman died. What does the brother do? So
again, מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum with a deaf woman, but it's
a rabbinic מצוה mitzvah because his brother was only married rabbinically. What
does he do? כונס ואם רצה להוציא יוציא. kones v'im ratza l'hotzi
yotzi. He can't do חליצה chalitza because she's not hearing, so because
she's deaf, so חליצה chalitza isn't an option. He does יבום, yibum,
but he can also give her a גט get if he wants
to after the יבום yibum because he's hearing. מת פיקח בן פיקחת
מה יעשה חרש בן חרשת. meis pikeach ben pikachas mah ya'aseh cheresh
ben chereshes. Now if the hearing brother died, what can this guy,
the חרש, cheresh, do? So he can't do חליצה chalitza because he's
a חרש. cheresh.
He can only do יבום, yibum, okay? But he can't give a
גט get after the יבום yibum because again, he's a חרש cheresh
and the יבום yibum is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So כונס ואינו מוציא לעולם.
kones v'eino motzi l'olam. He can only do יבום, yibum, he can't
give a גט. get. So we've now worked through all the permutations.
Again, a lot of this we covered yesterday or the two days
before. The biggest point to be made is the point that we
just said at the end, which is that there's a big difference
as a חרש cheresh if he gets married as a קידושין, kiddushin,
it's rabbinic and he can get divorced. But if he winds up
doing יבום, yibum, then he cannot go ahead
and give a גט. get. However, if she's the חרשת chereshes and
the man is a פיקח, pikeach, then you could have a יבום
yibum followed with a גט, get, and that's also building on the
principle at the beginning that the woman doesn't have to be a
בר דעת bar da'as in order for there to be a גט.
get. Yes?
How does it apply today?
What do you mean how does it apply? In terms of do
we treat חרש cheresh today as a חרש cheresh
and all that?
Yeah, you would. I mean, the גמרא gemara doesn't offer a solution
and I mean, it's really, look, thankfully, cases of יבום yibum are
rare, combined with these cases are rare and so on, but the
real possibility
of this being different is how the category of חרש cheresh and
חרשת chereshes changed, as I've been indicating. You know, there's a whole
development in הלכה halacha about whether to treat them as בני דעה
bnei de'ah nowadays because it's clear that they do have intellect and
knowledge and so on. Yeah?
In the case of the חרש cheresh and חרשת chereshes and then
the other sister being
a פיקחת, pikachas, we say that she's really stuck. Why don't we
just say, and again, why don't we just say אפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין,
afke'inhu rabanan l'kiddushin, why don't we just break the קידושין kiddushin to
begin with?
Yeah, it's a good question. When some of these are rabbinic, like
some of these are rabbinic,
there's not a good answer when we decide to say אפקעינהו afke'inhu
and when not. Like this is a case that really would call
for it. I don't know. It seems like I don't have a
good answer. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. אמר
רמי בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, we have a nice little
expository piece of גמרא gemara now. מה שנא חרש וחרשת דתקינו להו
רבנן נישואין ומה שנא שוטה ושוטה דלא תקינו להו רבנן נישואין? mah
shena cheresh v'chereshes d'tikinu lehu rabanan nisu'in v'mah shena shoteh v'shotah d'lo
tikinu lehu rabanan nisu'in?
This whole משנה mishnah is based on the idea that there's a
rabbinic קידושין kiddushin for חרש, cheresh, but we don't find
that there's a rabbinic קידושין kiddushin for a שוטה shoteh or שוטה,
shotah, somebody who is
not in their right mind, not mentally well. Okay, so what's the
difference? So how do you know that? דלא תקינו להו רבנן נישואין
דתניא, d'lo tikinu lehu rabanan nisu'in detanya, תני תנא ברייתא: tni tana
baraisa: שוטה וקטן שנשאו נשים, shoteh v'katan shenasu nashim, if
somebody who is not mentally well and a minor married women, ומתו
נשיהם פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום. umesu nisheihem peturos min hachalitza umin
hayibum.
There's no even rabbinic requirement of חליצה chalitza and יבום, yibum, it's
not even rabbinically recognized. So why is there a difference between a
deaf person and a person not in his right mind or a
קטן, katan, knowing that rabbinically those are all considered to be people
that are not of legal agency? So the גמרא gemara says: חרש
וחרשת דקיימא תקנתא דרבנן תקינו להו רבנן נישואין. cheresh v'chereshes dekayma takeinta
derabanan tikinu lehu rabanan nisu'in.
By the case of a deaf man or woman where the rabbinic
institution will stand, so they established it. שוטה ושוטה דלא קיימא תקנתא
דרבנן, shoteh v'shotah d'lo kayma takeinta derabanan, that when you're dealing with
somebody that is not mentally well, that the institution won't stand. Why
won't the institution stand? אין אדם דר עם נחש בכפיפה, ein adam
dar im nachash bikfiffa, that
because a person cannot live with a snake under the same roof.
So בכפיפה אחת לא תקינו רבנן נישואין, bikfiffa achas lo tikinu rabanan
nisu'in, they did not establish it,
which means that it
is very hard to live with somebody who's not mentally stable and
therefore the rabbis did feel that they were not. not going to
go ahead and create an institution of rabbinic קידושין, kiddushin, you know,
if such marriages are highly unstable. So ומאי שנא קטן דלא תקינו
רבנן נישואין? u'mai shna katan de'lo takinu rabanan nisuin?
Okay, but how about a minor? And you know, a minor, it's
not an unstable situation. Again, and we know that there was rabbinic
קידושין kiddushin for a קטנה, ktana, so why not for a קטן,
katan, why not for a minor boy? So the גמרא Gemara says,
דלא תקינו רבנן נישואין, d'lo takinu rabanan nisuin, וחרש תקינו ליה רבנן
נישואין, ve'charesh takinu lei rabanan nisuin, and they did for a חרש.
charesh. חרש דלא אתי לכלל נישואין, charesh d'lo ati lichlal nisuin,
because a חרש, charesh, if we don't create a rabbinic נישואין nisuin
marriage for a חרש, charesh, he'll never be able to have to
be married. So therefore תקינו רבנן נישואין, takinu rabanan nisuin, they
established this institution of rabbinic marriage to a because you know, they
want him to be able to be married and so you want
and you don't do it within a type of a, you know,
legal institution. קטן דאתי לכלל נישואין, katan d'ati lichlal nisuin, but a
minor that will grow up, לא תקינו רבנן נישואין, lo takinu rabanan
nisuin, they didn't have to create the institution. Wait till you grow
up, you know, what's the rush? You know, enjoy yourself till your
בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah or something. Anyway, so alright, so בקיצור, bekitzur,
that's a very good reason. Why create this new institution? What's the
need for it? Just wait till you grow up. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, now by the way, רש"י Rashi says תקינו ליה
רבנן נישואין, takinu lei rabanan nisuin, if you look like four lines
from the bottom, כדי שלא יבטל. kedei shelo yivatel. יבטל, yivatel, that
specifically has the connotation of יבטל yivatel from פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu.
Okay, so as opposed to just sort of saying like people, it's
an intrinsic good to be married, which is also true and the
גמרא Gemara discussed earlier, right? רש"י Rashi is also introducing the idea
of doing the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, although one
should say that even the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu,
if the person is not obligated in מצוות, mitzvos, we're also not
talking specifically about doing it from a מצוה mitzvah necessity, but from
an intrinsic good type of an idea. People want to be married,
they want to have kids, so the Rabbis created the institution of
נישואין nisuin for a חרש. charesh. There was no need to do
it for a קטן. katan. Okay, but now the obvious question is:
so why do you need to do it for a קטנה? ktana?
Okay. והרי קטנה דאתייא לכלל נישואין, ve'harei ktana d'asya lichlal nisuin, okay,
but a young girl will eventually be able to be old enough
to be married biblically, ותקינו רבנן נישואין, ve'takinu rabanan nisuin, and they
established it even when she had no father. Why did they need
to do
that? התם שלא ינהגו בה
מנהג הפקר, hasam shelo yinhagu bah minhag hefker, that is so that
she should not be taken sexually advantage of. If you have a
young girl that doesn't have a father, right, people will take sexual
advantage of her. So it's better to get her married and to
have a man that will protect her, you know, in order that,
you know, it's you know, that's just, you know, to protect her
own, you know, so to so that she herself will will be
protected. It's actually interesting, I was reading this thing about
about you know there’s a brother around potentially.
Yeah, you know, exactly. But there’s nobody who has like, you know,
who really sees her directly as as her, you know, in in
that way of of responsible. So look, this is something that, you
know, is it’s been all, you know, true for for millennia about
the idea of a woman attached to a man in the sense
that a man needs to to provide for her, to protect her,
and so on. So I guess I was particularly struck that I
was reading this big thing that’s been in the news the last
few months about about rape on campus, right? And people know about
this, about all these problems. Anyway, so this one woman was just
was was talking about like, yeah, you know, they tell you that
like, you know, like when you go to parties or this or
that, like, you know, you should say you’ve got a boyfriend or
you should pretend that you or somebody should agree with somebody pretend
you have a boyfriend so like you’ll be she’s like, what is
this? Like, you know, I can like I need a man without
a man I can’t like you know I need a man to
always be there to be protecting me? Like, or to you know,
or to pretend that there’s always some man there, right, that you
know, like so you know, this idea that even in today’s society,
right, women who do are not perceived of as having a man
to protect them, you know, might be, you know, taken more advantage
of. So it’s it’s not something that we've really grown out of,
you know, or that, you know, has left us. So it’s quite
it’s quite I don’t know, to me that was just shocking.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ומאי שנא קטנה דממאנת,
u'mai shna ktana de'memaenes, ומאי שנא חרשת דלא ממאנה? u'mai shna chareshes
d'lo memaana?
Why do they allow a קטנה ktana when you’ve done this rabbinic
קידושין kiddushin to do מיאון, miun, but they don’t allow a חרשת
chareshes to do מיאון, miun, right?
Even when she’s... you mean when she’s a קטנה? ktana?
As long as she’s a קטנה. ktana. So that’s going to be
the answer. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is, no, דאם כן ממני
ולא נסבי לה. de'im ken mimni ve'lo nasbi lah.
No, because if a חרשת chareshes can do מיאון miun her whole
marriage, who's going to want to marry a woman that any day
can do מיאון, miun, right? Like there's no commitment. Whereas by a
קטנה, ktana, it’s for the period that she's a קטנה ktana and
then it’ll be binding. Okay. ומאי שנא קטנה דאכלה בתרומה, u'mai shna
ktana d'achla be'terumah, ומאי שנא חרשת דלא אכלה בתרומה? u'mai shna chareshes
d'lo achla be'terumah? Now you have these two קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin d'rabanan,
קטנה ktana and חרשת.
chareshes. If she’s a
קטנה.
ktana. If a קטנה ktana is married to a כהן, kohen, she
can eat תרומה, terumah, even though she herself is not a כהנת,
kohennes, which is actually interesting, right? Why? I mean, תרומה terumah is
דאורייתא, d'oraisa, why would we let a קטנה ktana do it?
So גמרא Gemara sort of elsewhere, here it’s going to touch on
it, but elsewhere it develops the idea of two things. Number one
is if she's not obligated in מצוות, mitzvos, so, okay, she’s doing
an עבירה aveirah but big deal, but it’s not really a big
deal, I mean would we just סתם stam tolerate it? So the
other point is that we're talking about an assumption that we're dealing
with rabbinic תרומה, terumah, maybe nowadays all תרומה terumah is דרבנן, d'rabanan,
or maybe it’s on, you know, fine. fruits and not on grain
and it's דרבנן. derabbanan. So A, it's only a rabbinic prohibition, and
B, the person themselves, either as a קטנה ketanah or a חרשת,
chereshet, is not obligated in מצוות, Mitzvos, so therefore, we're going to
allow it if they're married to a כהן. Kohen. Because obviously כהן's
Kohen's going to want to feed his wife the תרומה Terumah that's
most of what he's got, right? And that's part of creating this
institution of rabbinic קידושין. Kiddushin. But the reality is we only allow
it by a קטנה, ketanah, we don't allow it by a חרשת.
chereshet. What's the difference? ומאי שנא קטנה דאכלה בתרומה ומאי חרשת דלא
אכלה בתרומה? Umai shena ketanah d'achlah b'Terumah u'mai chereshet d'lo achlah b'Terumah?
דתנן, Detnan, how do you know this is true? That only the
קטנה ketanah can and not the חרשת. chereshet. We taught in a
משנה. Mishnah. העיד רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא. He'id Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada.
Here we have רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada again.
על חרשת שהשיאה אביה שיוצאה בגט. Al chereshet she'hisiah aviha she'yotze b'get.
That's what we quoted in the משנה, Mishnah, that a חרשת chereshet
who's married by a father can be divorced by a גט, get,
because again, even if the קידושין דאורייתא, Kiddushin d'Oraisa, but the man
can still divorce even though she's a חרשת. chereshet. ועל קטנה בת
ישראל שניתת לכהן, Ve'al ketanah bas Yisroel she'nisais l'Kohen, and if a
minor girl who's married to a כהן, Kohen, even if it's rabbinic,
שאוכלת בתרומה, she'ocheles b'Terumah, that she eats תרומה. Terumah. ואילו חרשת לא
אכלה, Ve'ilu chereshet lo achlah, but it sounds like only the קטנה
ketanah can eat תרומה, Terumah, not the חרשת. chereshet. So what's the
difference? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. גזירה שמא ישיא חרש בחרשת.
Gezeirah shema yashi cheresh b'chereshet. We don't let a חרשת, chereshet, a
deaf woman married to a כהן, Kohen, eat תרומה Terumah because we're
afraid that she'll be married to a חרש cheresh man, a deaf
כהן. Kohen. So what? So the גמרא Gemara says, וליכול, v'lechol, so
and let her eat. קטן אוכל נבלות היא, Katan ochel neveilos hi,
if it's a minor or a non-minor but somebody who's not considered
right to be legally obligated. Right? The same way we allowed the
young girl, let's allow this case as well. So she's eating non-kosher
things, again in another גמרא Gemara explains that it's only non-kosher rabbinically,
right? תרומה Terumah for a non-כהן, Kohen, okay,
it's treated as non-kosher but it would be a rabbinic scenario. So
what? I mean, we allowed by קטנה, ketanah, allow it here. So
the גמרא Gemara says, גזירה שמא ישיא חרש בפיקחת. Gezeirah shema yashi
cheresh b'pikachas. Okay, no,
we're afraid that if we allow
a deaf woman married to a כהן Kohen to eat תרומה, Terumah,
we'll allow the reverse, which is a deaf כהן Kohen to have
his hearing wife eat תרומה. Terumah. And his hearing wife is obligated
in מצוות. Mitzvos. So the גמרא Gemara says and that would be
also only a rabbinic marriage because the man is deaf. So the
גמרא Gemara says, וחרש בפיקחת נמי ליכול בתרומה דרבנן. v'cheresh b'pikachas nami
lechol b'Terumah d'rabbanan. So what? Let her at least eat rabbinic תרומה.
Terumah. Okay, fine, that would be a case of an adult woman
eating תרומה Terumah and she's obligated in מצוות, Mitzvos, but let her
at least eat rabbinic תרומה Terumah because we
were willing to waive certain דרבנן derabbanan concerns like in the case
of the
קטנה, ketanah, let's waive it here. So the גמרא Gemara says, no.
גזירה דילמא אתי למיכל בתרומה דאורייתא. Gezeirah dilma asi l'meichal b'Terumah d'Oraisa.
No,
because once this woman is eating any תרומה, Terumah, it could easily
lead to תרומה דאורייתא. Terumah d'Oraisa. So the basic point is like
this:
that why do we not allow a deaf woman married to a
כהן Kohen to eat תרומה? Terumah? Because if we allow a deaf
woman married to a hearing man to eat תרומה, Terumah, it'll come
to the reverse, where it'll be a hearing woman married to a
deaf כהן Kohen eating תרומה. Terumah. And there, since the woman is
obligated in מצוות Mitzvos and she's eating תרומה Terumah and she shouldn't
be eating תרומה, Terumah, it'll very easily slide into her eating דאורייתא
d'Oraisa תרומה Terumah and actually violating an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'Oraisa. So
that's why we don't allow it in the deaf case. Now the
obvious question is, so say the same about the minor case. Why
would we not allow a if we allow a minor girl to
eat תרומה Terumah married to a כהן, Kohen, why aren't we afraid
that that will lead to the reverse,
which is when the כהן Kohen is a minor boy and he's
married to an adult
woman? Right? That's the problem. We don't allow one case because we're
afraid of the mirror image which will be a דאורייתא d'Oraisa problem.
So רש"י Rashi says, no, look. By חרש, cheresh, if either side
is a חרש, cheresh, it's the same דרבנן קידושין. derabbanan Kiddushin. So
we can assume that people will think if you allow it when
she's a חרשת chereshet and he's hearing, then we should allow the
reverse when the man is deaf and she's hearing. It's easy to
reverse those cases. But the case of the minor, especially in a
society where it's the girls who are very young that are being
married and not the men anyway, and number two, we only have
קידושין Kiddushin for a minor girl, not for a minor boy, we
won't come to allow the reverse when he's a minor and she's
not.
Unless the minor boy could also do יבום, Yibum, that's
the only way.
Right,
exactly. So you don't even have a rabbinic קידושין Kiddushin when the
boy is minor.
In the previous case, why can't a minor חרשת chereshet have מיאון?
miun?
Why can't a minor חרשת—because chereshet
she's—just that theory of well, she's still a minor.
Oh, she can.
She could.
When it says that they didn't establish for a חרשת, chereshet, it
meant from the dimension of her being a חרשת. chereshet. She's not
excluded from it if she's also a קטנה, ketanah, but her status
of a חרשת chereshet does not allow her to do מיאון. miun.
Okay.
So it seems like the גמרא Gemara was all framing it like
גזירה לגזירה, gezeirah l'gezeirah, at least the way...
Yeah, so רש"י Rashi somehow explains and you needed to go two
steps or whatever. I don't want to get into that. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומאי שנא קטנה דאית לה כתובה
ומאי שנא חרשת דלית לה כתובה? Umai shena ketanah d'is lah kesubah
u'mai shena chereshet d'leis lah kesubah? We're going to demonstrate in a
minute that within the rabbinic institution of קידושי קטנה, kidushei ketanah, there
was also a כתובה, kesubah, but not with the rabbinic institution of
קידושי חרשת. kidushei chereshet. Why is that? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: דאם כן ממינע ולא נסבי לה. de'im kein mimni v'lo
nasvi la. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara saying because חרשת chereshes is,
you know, again, sadly reflecting a sad societal reality that the case
of a deaf woman people are more, you know, more reluctant to
marry such a woman. So therefore, if there would also be the
obligation of כתובה, kesuva, nobody would want to marry her. So by
not having a כתובה, kesuva, it makes it more possible for her
to get married. And that's not seen to be the case of
a קטנה, ktana, because a קטנה ktana of course is going to
grow up.
That's looking to make it
more easy for her to get married? That is true. Again, I
guess it was assumed that in the balance this was done, this
was the best for her. Okay. וקטנה מנלן דאית לה כתובה? v'ktana
minalan de'is la kesuva? How do you know a קטנה ktana has
a כתובה? kesuva? דתנן, detnan, we turn in the משנה: Mishnah: הממאנת
והשניה והאיילונית, hama'enes v'hashniya v'ha'aylonis, if a woman refuses, right, a young
girl, or, so and she walks away, so remember when a girl
walks away from marriage it's like she was never married so she's
not going to get a כתובה. kesuva. Or a שניה, shniya, somebody
who's a secondary עריות, arayos, רבנן rabbinic עריות, arayos, so they didn't
establish a כתובה kesuva for that, obviously it's a type of a
fine. והאיילונית, v'ha'aylonis, and a woman who was an איילונית, aylonis, which
is a woman who had like, you know, never developed
sexual characteristics or whatever developed in an unusual way and anyway she's
seen as completely excluded from the possibility of having of having kids
and as a general rule assumed that the man did not want
to marry her had he known. מקח טעות. mekach ta'os. If he
consciously did it, it would be different, but it's assumed to be
מקח טעות. mekach ta'os. אין להן כתובה, ein lahen kesuva, in all
these cases, the first and the last one because it was never
a marriage, הממאנת hama'enes and איילונית, aylonis, and the middle one because
it was a forbidden marriage, so there's no כתובה. kesuva.
אבל, aval, so the גמרא Gemara comments fine, but הממאנת hama'enes remember
is a קטנה. ktana. So the point of the משנה Mishnah is
the reason the קטנה ktana doesn't have a כתובה kesuva is because
she did מיאון miun and she made it that they were never
married. So the implication of that is, אבל יוצאה בגט קטנה, aval
yotza b'get ktana, this is now the גמרא Gemara talking, were she
actually to have been divorced through a גט get and she was
a minor, not that she did מיאון miun but she was given
a גט get as a minor, יש לה כתובה. yesh la kesuva.
The implication would be she would have a כתובה. kesuva. That's a
pretty good deal, right? It's only because she did מיאון. miun. So
there we see a קטנה ktana has
כתובה. kesuva. וחרשת מנלן דלית לה כתובה? v'chereshes minalan de'leis la kesuva?
How do you know a חרשת chereshes doesn't have a כתובה? kesuva?
דתניא, detanya, we turn in the ברייתא: Braisah:
חרש ושוטה שנשאו פקחות, cheresh v'shoteh she'nas'u pikchos, if a man was
a חרש cheresh or a שוטה shoteh and married a hearing woman,
אף על פי שנתפקח החרש ונשתפה השוטה, af al pi she'nispakei'ach hacheresh
v'nishtafa hashoteh, even though they became hearing, they became, you know, better,
hearing or cured or whatever while they were married, אין להם עליהם
כלום. ein lahem aleihem klum. They have no כתובה kesuva obligations. Okay,
even the חרש, cheresh, I mean the שוטה shoteh there was not
even a רבנן rabbinic קידושין, kidushin, but even the חרש, cheresh, because
he could not act, the assumption being that since he was deaf
he could not, the man, you know, since he was in this
category of not having agency, although they established
קידושין kidushin and נישואין, nisu'in, they did not establish כתובה. kesuva. And
even if he presumably wrote a כתובה kesuva or maybe, well we'll
see about that, you know, maybe we wouldn't assume that he could
undertake, you know, his own financial obligations or that it would be
binding. So anyway, but certainly anyway, they got married, they don't have
any כתובה kesuva obligations. ורצו לקיימן יש להם כתובה, v'ratzu l'kayman yesh
lahem kesuva, if now that they're better they decide to continue with
the marriage, then that's, now we're dealing with a marriage דאורייתא D'oraisa
and now there will be a כתובה. kesuva. Okay, but it basically
starts with the idea that there was no כתובה kesuva automatically even
though there was a רבנן rabbinic קידושין kidushin and נישואין. nisu'in.
Meaning even then, then they write one now, like you want...
Well or even not writing it, just living together and continuing to
be married creates a רבנן, rabbinic, you know, automatically the רבנן rabbinic
institution of כתובה kesuva obligations kick in. Okay. כתובה kesuva obligations exist,
yeah it might be less or whatever, but okay.
Like at that moment, like the day they get better?
Yeah, I mean right, once they decide they're going to continue living
together and being married. פקח שנשא חרשת או שוטה, pikei'ach she'nasa chereshes
o shota, now let's say the man is well and the woman
is either deaf or not in her right mind, אפילו כתב לה
מאה מנה כתובתה קיימת. afilo kasav la mea mana kesuvasah kayames. So
here's the difference, meaning because he is a בר דעת, bar da'as,
if he chose to write a כתובה, kesuva, he could write a
million-dollar כתובה. kesuva. You want to go ahead and create a financial
obligation, you're געזונטהייט. gezundheit. The רבנן rabbis didn't institute כתובה, kesuva, but
if he wanted to, again, so that's the difference between if he's
the one that's well, or you know, where, you know,
in the first case where he was in the category of not
בר דעת, bar da'as, even if he undertook a financial obligation, it's
assumed that it won't be binding because he's considered not a בר
דעת. bar da'as. It's interesting, we allow him to get married but
we don't allow him to create, to undertake financial obligations. In the
second case however, in both cases there's no רבנן rabbinic institution of
כתובה, kesuva, but in the second case where he actually is a
בר דעת, bar da'as, then he, even though there's no institution of
כתובה kesuva because the woman he's marrying is a חרשת chereshes or
שוטה, shota, but he can undertake the obligation and it will be
binding. Okay? שאפילו כתב לה מאה מנה כתובתה קיימת, she'afilo kasav la
mea mana kesuvasah kayames, מפני שרצה לזוק בנכסיו. mipnei she'ratza lazuk binchasav.
He wanted to create a debt on his, you know, property, he's
entitled to, right? There's no רבנן rabbinic institution, but you want to
create an obligation, געזונטהייט. gezundheit. So anyway, in all these cases... cases
you see that if one of the side is a חרש cheresh
*cheresh*, there's no rabbinic כתובה ksuva *ketubah*. So טעמא דרצה *taama deratza*,
the only reason that there's a כתובה Ketubah *ketubah* obligation in the
second case is because he undertook it. הא לא רצה *ha lo
ratza*, if he didn't, אין לה *ein lah*, so the woman who
is a חרשה *cheresha* does not have a כתובה *ketubah*. So why
is this? So the reason is we said before, דאם כן *de'im
kein*, were they to institute a rabbinic כתובה *ketubah*, מימנע ולא נסבי
לה *mimne velo nasbi lah*, people would not want to marry her.
אי הכי *i hachi*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, פקחת לחרש לתקן
לה כתובה *pikachat lecheresh litkin lah ketubah*. So how about the first
case where he's the חרש cheresh *cheresh*? Where we also said there's
no כתובה *ketubah*. So why don't we say the reverse? She now
is the woman who's hearing, right? You got the case. She's hearing,
he's not. Right? The basically that the ברייתא brayta, *braita* we just
quoted made it clear that if one of the side is not
hearing, no כתובה *ketubah*. So we said when she's not hearing, no
כתובה *ketubah*, we waived the כתובה *ketubah* so people would want to
marry her. Okay, when he's not hearing, why don't we insist that
there's a כתובה *ketubah*, because we would say a hearing woman wouldn't
want to marry this person unless, you know, minimally she had the
same protection, right, as any other woman? Why do we actually, we're
making it, we're creating a disincentive for this woman to get married?
And we're just trying to say we're trying to make
it easier for this man to get married, right?
For somebody to marry this man. Okay, by waiving the כתובה *ketubah*
it's a disincentive for you know, to marry this man. So why
are we doing that? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אי הכי
פקחת לחרש לתקן לה כתובה *i hachi pikachat lecheresh litkin lah ketubah*,
let's have a כתובה *ketubah*, דאם כן מימנע ולא מינסבי *de'im kein
mimne velo minsabi*, because otherwise people won't want to marry him. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, יתר שהאיש רוצה לישא אשה רוצה להנשא
*yoter mishe'ish rotze liso isha rotza lehinase*. So famous line in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, which is "more that a man wants to get
married, a woman wants to get married." So therefore, it's, you know,
it's we have to create more incentives for men to marry women
than we have to do for women to marry men. Okay, which
doesn't exactly explain. Look, I, you know, we can't read this. On
the one hand, what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is describing is sadly
a societal reality, you know, as we very well know today, right,
you know, and it's very, you know, that the people, you know,
for big, small and everything in the middle, little things, somebody's not
perfect in whatever their idea of perfection is, they say whatever, nobody
wants to marry them, or whatever. So that's number one just a
tragic reality and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is, but it is a
reality and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is dealing with it. Okay. But
well, the answer is that, which also I think is a reality,
which is that, you know, it's a lot easier for men to
get married than for women to get married. So therefore, if the
woman is the one who has something that makes her, you know,
different,
and here particularly, you know, she's deaf or שוטה Shota. *shota* and
so on, certainly שוטה *shota* even more challenging, you know, you have
to create an incentive, because it's harder for women to get married,
so you have to, or you have to,
what? But when it's the man who's got the issue, you don't
have to create an incentive, because it's easier for men to get
married.
Why doesn't she
be like any other case? Right. So that's the question that hasn't
been answered. Okay, fine, you don't have to create an incentive, you
know, you don't have to give like a double כתובה *ketubah* for
a woman who'll marry this man. But why not give her like
the normal protection? Right. So that's not clear. It seems like the
answer is is that you don't give the, because since he's a
חרש cheresh. *cheresh*, since a כתובה *ketubah* is him creating a financial
obligation, and he's not a בר דעת bar daas *bar da'at*, there's
some sense that it's not fair to, you know, to create,
to you know, to impose this financial obligation on him.
Why can't he do it then? You know, meaning like, they should
still do it, you know what I mean?
Like I understand, meaning not that he has to create a contract,
but that it just is his obligation. Right, I mean, if we're
trusting him enough as enough of a בר דעת bar daas. *bar
da'at* to get married. Right. So that is a very good question.
Like it does not really answer it. Everybody understands the problem is
it explains why they didn't have to create an additional incentive for
somebody to marry this man. It doesn't create why they created a
disincentive right by taking away the כתובה *ketubah*. Why shouldn't the woman
have the normal protection? Right. And there's not and it seems that
it's only based on the fact that like he's not a בר
דעת bar daas *bar da'at*, so somehow that would be seen as
like not fair to him or something. But there's really not a
good answer. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
Now. ההוא חרש cheresh דהוה בשיבבותיה
דרב מלכיו *hahu cheresh dehavah beshivuteih deRav Malkio*. There was a certain
חרש cheresh, *cheresh* that was in the neighborhood of רב מלכיו *Rav
Malkio*, אנסיבה איתתא *ansivah itteta*. He married a woman. וכתב לה ארבע
מאה זוזי מנכסיה *vechatav lah arba meah zuzei minechaseih*. He wrote a
big כתובה *ketubah*, 400 זוז *zuz*.
So what we've said until now made it sound like a חרש
cheresh *cheresh* cannot undertake a כתובה *ketubah* obligation, even if he wanted
to he couldn't because he's not a בר דעת bar da'as, *bar
da'at*, right? So even if he wanted to he couldn't. And here
presumably רב מלכיו *Rav Malkio* allowed him to write a big כתובה
*ketubah*. אמר רבא *amar Rava*: מאן חכם כרב מלכיו *man chacham keRav
Malkio*? Who is wise like רב מלכיו *Rav Malkio*? דגברא רבה הוא
*degavrah rabbah hu*, because of he's such a great, you know, rabbi,
he was able to on his authority do this, even though it
sounded like before you're not allowed to do this. Why? קסבר *kasavar*,
because he's of the opinion: אילו רצה שפחה לשמשו מי לא זבנינן
ליה *ilu ratza shifcha leshamsho mi lo zavninan leh*? Let's say, you
know, he wanted to go to buy a slave woman, you know,
we would what, we would allow him? Meaning it's true that חרש
cheresh *cheresh* maybe biblically cannot
engage in transactions. Obviously we would allow him to engage in certain
types of financial transactions that were necessary for and see them as
legally binding that were necessary for him to get along with his
life. So he could actually if he could buy a woman as
a slave woman, you know, why couldn't he go ahead and pay
a lot of money for a wife, you know, and write a
כתובה? So, so כל שכן הכא דאיכא תרתי, kol shekein hacha d'ika
tarti, so here the woman will be able to take care of
his domestic needs as a wife and it'll be his wife. So
why should we allow, which is sort of like, you know, what
what we were saying Michael was saying before, which is so why
not establish a כתובה for such a woman rabbinically? Okay, normally, you
know, חרש cheresh doesn't undergo financial, but for God's sake if he's
getting married, why don't we, you know, why is it unrealistic to
do the whole package and to protect the woman who's going to
be entering into this marriage?
So yeah, so there
is not really a good explanation why and it's one thing to
say maybe okay to assume a greater obligation we won't let him,
but to have the normal obligation, yeah, that's a real question. אמר
רב חייא בר אשי אמר שמואל: אשת
חרש אין חייבין עליה אשם תלוי.
Amar Rav Chiyya bar Ashi
amar Shmuel eishes cheresh ein chayavin aleha asham talui. Now we're getting
to the question, now we turn to, so that was a very
lovely exposition of like all of the differences between חרש cheresh and
קטנה ketanah and חרשת chereshet and like what what the package of
rabbinic קידושין kidushin is about. Now we turn to the question of
and you'll remember this we had this a day or two ago
about how much is it only purely rabbinic. Remember the גמרא Gemara
before had a question is it quasi קידושין, kidushin, is it ספק
קידושין, safek kidushin, but this question is not just going to be
about קידושין, kidushin, this question is also going to be about the
status of a חרש. cheresh To what degree is a חרש cheresh
really out of the category of a בר דעת bar da'as, and
this is again an important גמרא Gemara for you know the possibility
that that category continues to develop afterwards. So let's take a look.
It says like this. אמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר שמואל Amar
Rav Chiyya bar Ashi amar Shmuel: אשת חרש אין חייבין עליה אשם
תלוי. Eishes cheresh ein chayavin aleha asham talui. The wife of a
חרש, cheresh if a person, another man has sex with her, is,
you know, is that an act of adultery? So you do not
have to bring a doubtful אשם, asham, an אשם תלוי asham talui
is something you bring when it's a when you might have done
an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'oraisa. So the man who did this, it's
not even a doubtful דאורייתא d'oraisa of adultery, which basically means it's
a purely rabbinic קידושין, kidushin, it's not a possible דאורייתא d'oraisa at
all. You don't bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So לימא מסייע
ליה, leima misayei lei, so that which is basically a way of
saying that a חרש cheresh, is fully out of the category of
בר דעת. bar da'as So the גמרא Gemara says לימא מסייע ליה,
leima misayei lei, let me try to prove it to you. חמשה
לא יתרומו ואם תרמו אין תרומתן תרומה. Chamisha lo yitremu v'im tormu
ein trumatan truma. Five people can't take תרומה truma and if they
do it's not binding, it's not meaningful at all, which means that
it's biblically meaningless because if it's right, because if it's biblically binding
and rabbinically we don't like it then it still would be תרומה
truma because it would have a biblical status of תרומה. truma.
If they say it's nothing, means that it's nothing even right, even
biblically.
So if the תרומה truma falls back into טבל tevel there's no
problem, you can eat the whole thing. Exactly, exactly. ואלו הן, V'eilu
hein, and these are the five people
that don't even that biblically do nothing in terms of the תרומה.
truma. חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh shoteh v'katan, those three, right, the deaf,
the person not in his right mind and the minor, והתורם את
שאינו שלו, v'hatorem es she'eino shelo, if it's not yours, unless you're
made an agent it's not good, ועובד כוכבים שתרם של ישראל אפילו
ברשות ישראל, v'oveid kochavim shetaram shel yisrael afilu birshus yisrael, or a
non-Jew who did it even if he was made an agent or
given permission, but he's not considered to be an agent and can't
take תרומה. truma. Okay, אין תרומתו תרומה, ein trumato truma, it's not
good. So you see that's a good proof that a חרש cheresh
is considered completely excluded. So aren't we saying the same thing? The
גמרא Gemara says not necessarily. הוא דאמר כרבי אליעזר, Hu d'amar k'Rabbi
Eliezer, it's possible that actually שמואל Shmuel would hold like רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, that generally a חרש cheresh, is maybe a ספק. safek.
דתניא רבי יצחק אומר משום רבי אליעזר תרומת חרש לא תצא לחולין.
Detanya Rabbi Yitzchak omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer trumas cheresh lo seitzei l'chulin.
If a חרש cheresh takes תרומה, truma, it is not it cannot
be considered to be oh not תרומה truma at all and just
like חולין. chulin. מפני שהוא ספק, Mipnei shehu safek, says very clearly
that a חרש's cheresh. תרומה truma is doubtful, meaning that a חרש's
cheresh status is doubtful whether he's a בר דעת bar da'as or
not. So אי סבירא ליה כרבי אליעזר, ei sevira lei k'Rabbi Eliezer,
one minute, if he holds that a חרש's cheresh status is doubtful,
אשם תלוי אמאי לא מיחייב? asham talui amai lo michayev? So if
a man sleeps with a wife of a חרש, cheresh he should
be a doubtful adultery דאורייתא d'oraisa and have to bring a sacrifice,
a sacrifice for doubtful sin. The גמרא Gemara says look, technically you're
right, but this is a technical point of אשם תלוי. asham talui.
באומר חתיכה משתי חתיכות. B'omer chaticha mishtei chatichos. For אשם תלוי, asham
talui, here the you know, this is a whole discussion by אשם
תלוי, asham talui, but the question is if I eat a piece
of something that might be I don't know, חמץ chametz on פסח.
Pesach. Do I bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? Ah, Michael says,
oh what are you talking about, didn't you hear that some of
the stuff from that store is חמץ? chametz? Okay, but whatever, who
knows what the status was, it's just an abstract doubt. Do you
bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? That's not, so that's one case,
that's that's just a doubt. The other point is there are two
pieces in front of me because you know here I Michael invites
me to his house and he has ספרדי Sefardi מצה matzah which
looks just like pizza, pita, right? So I go ahead and I
eat something that I think is ספרדי Sefardi מצה matzah and it
turns out that there was actually real חמץ chametz pizza right by
it and one of them was pizza and one of them was
מצה matzah and we don't know which one I ate. So that's
called חתיכה משתי חתיכות. chaticha mishtei chatichos. There's a concrete איסור דאורייתא
issur d'oraisa in front of you and the other one was מצה.
matzah. היתר, heter, and you don't know which one you ate. That's
a classic case of אשם תלוי, asham talui, when there was the
concrete possibility, the object that you could have done the איסור דאורייתא
issur d'oraisa with, as opposed to, oh, maybe, I don't know, it's
a doubt. That would not be. So what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is, שמואל Shmuel might have just been saying a technical point
in אשם תלוי. asham talui. Maybe he holds that a חרש cheresh
is doubt, is a doubtful בר דעת, bar da'as and that actually
if a man were to sleep with the wife of a חרש,
cheresh it would be a, you know, they'd be doing a doubtful
act of adultery דאורייתא, d'oraisa, okay, but still no אשם תלוי, asham
talui, because it's not like, you know, one object is אסור, assur,
one object is מותר mutter type of a thing, it's just a
doubt what the nature of the status is. Okay, so the point
is that might have been a technical point in terms of אשם
תלוי, asham talui, but maybe it's possible to hold like רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer position that a חרש cheresh, is a ספק, safek, and
that becomes the important point that we're going to focus on, which
is the status of a חרש. cheresh Is a חרש cheresh definitely
not a בר דעת, bar da'as or is he a ספק בר
דעת? safek bar da'as? And we have now introduced a new idea
that a חרש cheresh is a ספק בר דעת. safek bar da'as.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
ומי
בעי רבי אליעזר חתיכה משתי חתיכות, u'mi bay Rabbi Eliezer chaticha mishtei
chatichot, you're saying he's going like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that a
חרש cheresh, is a ספק, safek, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer normally
doesn't need there to be for an אשם תלוי asham talui for
there to be two pieces. דתניא, Dehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כוי, koy, which is this animal
that's a cross between a חיה chaya and a בהמה, behemah, so
you don't know whether the חלב, chelev, the fat, is forbidden or
not, חייב ואוכל בו אשם תלוי, chayav v'ochel bo asham talui, you're
חייב chayav for the fat an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, and
that's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
that that's how you treat a ספק safek even if it's not
one piece out of two, so the case of a wife of
a חרש cheresh should also be an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So
שמואל סבר רבי אליעזר בחדא ופליג ליה בחדא. Shmuel savar Rabbi Eliezer
b'chada u'puleig lei b'chada. So okay, since when does שמואל Shmuel have
to hold all the positions of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? He holds
like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer maybe that a חרש cheresh is a
ספק בר דעת, safek bar da'as, but he doesn't agree that you
bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for cases of just abstract ספק.
safek. To bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, you would need two
objects, so therefore in the case of the wife of the חרש,
cheresh there would be no אשם תלוי. asham talui. So that's the
אשם תלוי asham talui issue. But again, back to us, what's interesting
is the idea that a חרש cheresh might be a ספק. safek.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
איכא דאמרי אמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר שמואל, Ika d'amri, Amar
Rav Chiya bar Ashi, Amar Shmuel, אשת חרש חייבין עליה אשם תלוי,
eishes cheresh chayavin aleha asham talui, that actually he explicitly said you
are חייב chayav an אשם תלוי, asham talui, that he completely made
a blunt, an explicit statement that it is a, that the חרש
Cheresh is a ספק בר דעת, safek bar da'as, and therefore his
wife is ספק safek his wife דאורייתא. d'oraisa. מיתיבי, Meisvei, how could
you say that, don't we say חמישה לא יתרומו, chamisha lo yitrumu,
the five can't take, and this by a חרש Cheresh, it's absolutely
not תרומה? trumah? No, סבר לה כרבי אליעזר, savar lah ke'Rabbi Eliezer,
he holds like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says it's a ספק
תרומה. safek trumah. So now we are, what's fascinating again and you
have to understand how important this is in terms of the contemporary
discussions of the status of a חרש, Cheresh, is that the גמרא
Gemara is now, throughout all of ש"ס, Shas, you would say who
are the people that are not בר דעת bar da'as in ש"ס?
Shas? חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan, חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh
v'katan, right? So it's always that trio. Now we are finding that
there's a position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that a חרש Cheresh
is a ספק בר דעת. safek bar da'as. And the גמרא is
actually focusing on that position, and actually has one version of שמואל
Shmuel explicitly stating that position. Okay, so now we're going to explore
that idea. בעי רב אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi
asked, מה טעמא דרבי אליעזר, mah ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer, what's the reasoning
of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? מיפשט פשיטא ליה דעתא קלישא הוא, Mifsha
pshita lei d'cheresh da'ata klisha hu, is it clear to him that
a חרש Cheresh has like weaker דעת, da'as, feeble, yeah, I guess,
I'd rather not say that, that has a lot of negative connotations,
weaker דעת. da'as. So I know, but okay, so A, he might
not be as intelligent, again this is all through the גמרא's lens,
as other people, but not everybody is as intelligent as everybody else,
that doesn't exclude somebody from the בר דעת Bar Da'at. category. So
that itself would not do it. That, but okay, that's starting point
number one, but that's not really so relevant. ומי מספקא ליה, U'mi
mesafka lei, here's his question, אי דעתא צלותא אי לאו דעתא
צלותא,
ee da'ata tzlusa,
ee lav da'ata tzlusa, whether his, whether his דעת da'as is clear,
צלול tzalul is clear, right? So there's a difference between how highly
intelligent somebody is and whether they think clearly. Just because somebody is
not highly intelligent or like even like you know, of low intelligence,
and again this is all the גמרא's perspective obviously, you know, but
that does not make somebody not a legitimate legal agent and somebody
not a בר דעת Bar Da'at within הלכה, halacha, not everybody is
as intelligent as everybody else, right? But if somebody can't think clearly,
I mean, you know, that is, you know, then that's a problem,
like he can't reason clearly, can't think clearly, and whatever, that's different
than just not being so intelligent. And that would put somebody out
of the בר דעת Bar Da'at. category. So can't, so therefore that's
is this what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says? His question is, because
the גמרא doesn't want to think that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer like
really thinks that a חרש Cheresh, is just as intelligent as everybody
else, the גמרא assumes for granted that nobody would think that, but
fine,
but being not as intelligent would not put him out of the
בר דעת Bar Da'at, category, but what would is not thinking clearly.
And maybe,
meaning we all see, look, in a time where they did not
have schools for the deaf and they didn't have sign language and
whatever, a חרש Cheresh is going to act unusual within normal society,
he can't communicate right and so on, and he can't hear and
he can't make normal sounds and so on. Okay, so he's clearly
acting unusual. So do you interpret that as just lack of intelligence
or do you interpret that as not able to think clearly? And
only if you're in category two are you not in the בר
דעת. Bar Da'at. So maybe that's what רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's question
is. ולעולם חדא דעתא הוא, U'l'olam chada data hu,
and he always though has is of the same state of
mind, and we just don't know though which side of the fence
he is in terms of thinking clearly or not. או דלמא, O
dilma, or do we say, פשיטא ליה דדעתיה קלישא ולאו דעתיה צלולה
הוא. pshita lei de'daiteih klisha ve'lav daiteih tzelula hu. He knows that
no, he actually not only is he
not weaker intelligence, but also he doesn't think clearly. Okay, so then
what's his question? והכא היינו טעמא, Ve'hacha hainu ta'ama, this is his
concern, כיון דאית עתים חלים ועתים שוטה, Kivan de'it itim chalin ve'itim
shota, sometimes he does think clearly and sometimes he doesn't think clearly.
Okay, so the point is it's not that he's a stable state
of mind and we're trying to determine it, it's that we think
sometimes the חרש Cheresh will act more normally than other times. So
maybe sometimes he's thinking clearly and sometimes he's not. So therefore that's
the doubt. So the doubt is, meaning, and it's a question about
whether you sort of say the entire category of a חרש, Cheresh...
I don't know how to categorize it. Everybody's a חרש, I don't
know which side of the fence they fall on whether they're all
בר דעת Bar Da'at. or all not בר דעת. Bar Da'at That's
the first way of thinking. But the other way of thinking is
no, this individual, I don't know if this is a moment when
you were thinking clearly or not. Okay, do you understand the difference?
It's a big difference. So the גמרא says, למאי נפקא מינה, Le'mai
na fka mina, what practical difference would there be? להוציא אשתו בגט,
Le'hotzi ishto be'get, if a חרש married a woman and then he
wanted to divorce her. Now our משנה Mishnah says you can do
it, but maybe according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he couldn't. Why?
אי אמרת חדא דעתא הוא, I amarta chada data hu, if he's
always of the same state of mind, כקידושין כך גירושין. ke'kidushin kach
gerushin. So if the קידושין Kidushin was דאורייתא, De'oraita, the גירושין Gerushin
would be דאורייתא. De'oraita. If the קידושין Kidushin was דרבנן, De'rabbanan, then
the גירושין Gerushin would be דרבנן. De'rabbanan. But it's always the same
thing, all חרשים Chereshim always the same thing, we just don't know
which one they are. But אי אמרת, I amarta, so ואי אמרת
עתים חלים עתים שוטה, ve'i amarta itim chalin itim shota,
but if we don't know if this in particular person what his
state of mind was at any given time, if that's true, so
עתים שוטה, itim shota, קידושי מצי מקדש, kidushei matzi mekadesh, so the
קידושין Kidushin is good because it's either good דאורייתא De'oraita or דרבנן,
De'rabbanan, וגירושי לא מצי מגרש, ve'gerushei lo matzi megaresh, but he couldn't
divorce her because maybe when he did the קידושין Kidushin he was
in a clear state of mind, and now that he's coming to
write the גט, Get, he's not in a clear state of mind.
So מאי, Mai, so what do we say? Right, you would think
you could test him. Let's see if he could write a גט.
Get. Right. I know, it's funny. So תיקו, Teyku, so we don't
know. But what is really important you should know for thinking of
future הלכה Halacha is here you have the גמרא recognizing that חרש—it
never has this doubt by a שוטה. It only has this doubt
by a חרש, right? And the גמרא recognizing that it's not so
black and white what the status of a חרש is according to
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And therefore maybe even according to—first of all,
there's some גאונים, Gaonim, I should point out, that seem to פסקן
Pasken like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and seem to actually indicate—I'll try
to find it, I found some גאונים Gaonim who actually seem to
indicate not only do we פסקן Pasken it's a ספק, Safek, but
that if there's evidence that he is a בר דעת, that he
would be treated as a בר דעת. Okay, so once you have
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position,
and then you'd have to have a כתובה if he gets married.
Yeah, but then, but then you could treat a חרש as a
בר דעת. Right. And once you have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
certainly the second version of רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position, which basically
says we don't know, in a particular case, it's not a category
decision, it's a case by case, then anytime we have evidence in
a particular case about that person, we could put him into the
בר דעת category. Right. So that's certainly within the גאונים, Gaonim, but
of course if we don't פסקן Pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
it becomes a little bit more theoretical. But nevertheless, it's an idea
that certainly gets developed in the last I guess few hundred years.
Yes. So we'll end here for now. Go ahead.
Just back to the discussion. It says well maybe we mean that
the the חרש...